<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en" dir="ltr">
<head>
<meta charset="UTF-8" />
<title>TARLTONS PRETTIE COUNTRIE IESTS. - Richard Tarlton Project</title>
<meta name="generator" content="MediaWiki 1.17.0" />
<meta name="robots" content="noindex,follow" />
<link rel="shortcut icon" href="/favicon.ico" />
<link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/opensearch_desc.php" title="Richard Tarlton Project (en)" />
<link rel="EditURI" type="application/rsd+xml" href="http://www.lcc.gatech.edu/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/api.php?action=rsd" />
<link rel="alternate" type="application/atom+xml" title="Richard Tarlton Project Atom feed" href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php?title=Special:RecentChanges&amp;feed=atom" />
<link rel="stylesheet" href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/load.php?debug=false&amp;lang=en&amp;modules=mediawiki.legacy.commonPrint%2Cshared&amp;only=styles&amp;printable=1&amp;skin=twentyten&amp;*" />
<meta name="ResourceLoaderDynamicStyles" content="" />
</head>
<body class="mediawiki ltr ns-0 ns-subject page-TARLTONS_PRETTIE_COUNTRIE_IESTS skin-twentyten">
<div id="wrapper" class="hfeed">
	<div id="header">
		<div id="masthead">
			<div id="branding" role="banner">
				<h1 id="site-title">
					<a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Main_Page" rel="home">
						Richard Tarlton Project					</a>
				</h1>
				<div id="site-description">From Richard Tarlton Project</div> 
								<img src="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/skins/twentyten/headers/tarltonheader.jpg" alt="Header image" />
			</div><!-- #branding -->

			<div id="access" role="navigation">
				<div class="menu">
					<ul>
												<li class="page_item">
							<a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Main_Page">Home</a>
						</li>
												<li class="page_item">
							<a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/The_Project">About the Project</a>
						</li>
												<li class="page_item">
							<a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Tarlton_Biography">Biography</a>
						</li>
												<li class="page_item">
							<a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Touring_with_the_Queen%27s_Men">Tarlton and the Queen's Men</a>
						</li>
												<li class="page_item">
							<a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/TarltonsJests">Tarlton's Jests</a>
						</li>
												<li class="page_item">
							<a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Resources">Resources and Further Reading</a>
						</li>
												<li class="page_item">
							<a href="http://www.lcc.gatech.edu/~djakacki3/tarlton/blog/">Blog</a>
						</li>
											</ul>
				</div>
			</div><!-- #access -->
		</div><!-- #masthead -->
	</div><!-- #header -->

	<div id="main" >
		<div id="container">
			<div id="content" role="main">			
				<div>
					<h2 class="entry-title">TARLTONS PRETTIE COUNTRIE IESTS.</h2>
					<div class="entry-meta">
											</div><!-- .entry-meta -->
					
					<div class="entry-content">
						<p><b>OVERVIEW.</b>
</p>
<table id="toc" class="toc"><tr><td><div id="toctitle"><h2>Contents</h2></div>
<ul>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-1"><a href="#Tarltons_wit_betweene_a_Bird_and_a_Woodcocke."><span class="tocnumber">1</span> <span class="toctext">Tarltons wit betweene a Bird and a Woodcocke.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-2"><a href="#Tarltons_Iest_of_a_Gridiron."><span class="tocnumber">2</span> <span class="toctext">Tarltons Iest of a Gridiron.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-3"><a href="#Tarltons_answere_in_defence_of_his_flat_nose."><span class="tocnumber">3</span> <span class="toctext">Tarltons answere in defence of his flat nose.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-4"><a href="#Tarltons_Iest_of_a_Bristowman."><span class="tocnumber">4</span> <span class="toctext">Tarltons Iest of a Bristowman.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-5"><a href="#A_Iest_broken_of_Tarlton_by_a_Country_Gentleman."><span class="tocnumber">5</span> <span class="toctext">A Iest broken of Tarlton by a Country Gentleman.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-6"><a href="#How_Tarlton_made_one_of_his_company_vtterly_forsweare_drunkennesse."><span class="tocnumber">6</span> <span class="toctext">How Tarlton made one of his company vtterly forsweare drunkennesse.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-7"><a href="#How_Tarlton_saued_his_head_from_cutting_off."><span class="tocnumber">7</span> <span class="toctext">How Tarlton saued his head from cutting off.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-8"><a href="#How_Tarlton_escaped_imprisonment."><span class="tocnumber">8</span> <span class="toctext">How Tarlton escaped imprisonment.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-9"><a href="#How_Tarlton_deceiued_a_Countrey_wench."><span class="tocnumber">9</span> <span class="toctext">How Tarlton deceiued a Countrey wench.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-10"><a href="#How_Tarlton_went_to_kill_Crowes."><span class="tocnumber">10</span> <span class="toctext">How Tarlton went to kill Crowes.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-11"><a href="#How_a_poore_Beggerman_ouer-reached_Tarlton_by_his_wit."><span class="tocnumber">11</span> <span class="toctext">How a poore Beggerman ouer-reached Tarlton by his wit.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-12"><a href="#Of_Tarltons_pleasant_answere_to_a_Gallant.2C_by_the_high-way_side."><span class="tocnumber">12</span> <span class="toctext">Of Tarltons pleasant answere to a Gallant, by the high-way side.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-13"><a href="#How_Tarlton_would_haue_drowned_his_wife."><span class="tocnumber">13</span> <span class="toctext">How Tarlton would haue drowned his wife.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-14"><a href="#How_Tarlton_made_his_Will_and_Testament."><span class="tocnumber">14</span> <span class="toctext">How Tarlton made his Will and Testament.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-15"><a href="#How_Tarlton_called_a_Gentleman_Knaue_by_craft."><span class="tocnumber">15</span> <span class="toctext">How Tarlton called a Gentleman Knaue by craft.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-16"><a href="#Tarltons_Iest_of_a_Country_wench."><span class="tocnumber">16</span> <span class="toctext">Tarltons Iest of a Country wench.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-17"><a href="#How_Tarlton_deceiued_an_Inne-holder_at_Sandwich."><span class="tocnumber">17</span> <span class="toctext">How Tarlton deceiued an Inne-holder at Sandwich.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-18"><a href="#Of_Tarltons_Wrongfull_accusation."><span class="tocnumber">18</span> <span class="toctext">Of Tarltons Wrongfull accusation.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-19"><a href="#Tarlton_deceived_by_a_Country_wench."><span class="tocnumber">19</span> <span class="toctext">Tarlton deceived by a Country wench.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-20"><a href="#How_Tarlton_could_not_abide_a_Cat.2C_and_deceiued_himselfe."><span class="tocnumber">20</span> <span class="toctext">How Tarlton could not abide a Cat, and deceiued himselfe.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-21"><a href="#How_Tarlton_and_his_oastesse_of_Waltham_met."><span class="tocnumber">21</span> <span class="toctext">How Tarlton and his oastesse of Waltham met.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-22"><a href="#Tarltons_meeting_with_his_Countrey_acquaintance_at_Ilford."><span class="tocnumber">22</span> <span class="toctext">Tarltons meeting with his Countrey acquaintance at Ilford.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-23"><a href="#How_a_Maid_drove_Tarlton_to_a_Non-plus."><span class="tocnumber">23</span> <span class="toctext">How a Maid drove Tarlton to a Non-plus.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-24"><a href="#Tarltons_answer_to_a_question."><span class="tocnumber">24</span> <span class="toctext">Tarltons answer to a question.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-25"><a href="#Tarlton_desire_of_enough_for_money."><span class="tocnumber">25</span> <span class="toctext">Tarlton desire of enough for money.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-26"><a href="#How_Tarltons_Dogge_lickt_vp_six_pence."><span class="tocnumber">26</span> <span class="toctext">How Tarltons Dogge lickt vp six pence.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-27"><a href="#Tarltons_Iest_of_a_Horse_and_a_Man."><span class="tocnumber">27</span> <span class="toctext">Tarltons Iest of a Horse and a Man.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-28"><a href="#Tarltons_talke_with_a_pretty_Woman."><span class="tocnumber">28</span> <span class="toctext">Tarltons talke with a pretty Woman.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-29"><a href="#A_Iest_of_Tarlton_to_a_great_man."><span class="tocnumber">29</span> <span class="toctext">A Iest of Tarlton to a great man.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-30"><a href="#Tarltons_Iest_to_a_maid_in_the_darke."><span class="tocnumber">30</span> <span class="toctext">Tarltons Iest to a maid in the darke.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-31"><a href="#Tarltons_Iest_to_a_Dogge."><span class="tocnumber">31</span> <span class="toctext">Tarltons Iest to a Dogge.</span></a></li>
<li class="toclevel-1 tocsection-32"><a href="#Notes"><span class="tocnumber">32</span> <span class="toctext">Notes</span></a></li>
</ul>
</td></tr></table>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Tarltons_wit_betweene_a_Bird_and_a_Woodcocke."> Tarltons wit betweene a Bird and a Woodcocke. </span></h2>
<p>In the Citie of Glocester, Master Bird of the Chappell met with Tarlton, who [soyfull to regreet other], when to visit his friends: amongst the rest, M. Bird at the Queens Chappell visited Master Woodcock of the College, where meeting, many friendly speeches past, amongst which, M. Woodcocke challenged M. Bird of kin: who mused that he was of his affinitie and hee neuer knew it: yes sayes M. Woodcocke, euery Woodcocke is a Bird, therefore it must needs be so. Lord, Sir, sayes Tarlton, you are wide, for though euery Woodcocke be a Bird, yet euery Bird is not a Woodcocke. So M. Woodcocke like a Woodcocke bit his lip, and mum budged was silent.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li><li> Note: "wide" may be a typographical error - the sentence would make better sense if the word were "wise".
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Tarltons_Iest_of_a_Gridiron."> Tarltons Iest of a Gridiron. </span></h2>
<p>While the Queens Plaiers lay in Worcester Citie to get money, it was his custome oft to sing extempory of Theams giuen him: amongst which they were appoynted to play the next day: now one fellow of the City amongst the rest, that seemed quaint of conceit, to lead other youths with his fine wit, gaue out that the next day hee would giue him a Theam, to put him to a non plus: diuers of his friends acquainted with the same, expected some rare conceit: Well, the next day came, and my gallant gaue him his inuention in two lines, which was this this:
</p>
<dl><dd><i>Me thinkes it is a thing vnfit.</i><br />
</dd><dd><i>To see a Gridiron turne the spit.</i><br />
</dd></dl>
<p>The people laughed at this, thinking his wit knew no answers thereunto, which angered Tarlton exceedingly, and presently with a smile looking about, when they expected wonders, he put it off thus:
</p>
<dl><dd><i>Me thinkes it is a thing vnfit,</i><br />
</dd><dd><i>To see an Asse haue any wit.</i><br />
</dd></dl>
<p>The people hooted for ioy, to see the Theame-giuer dasht, who like a dog with his taile betweene his legs, left the place: But such commendations Tarlton got, that hee supt with the Bailiffe that night, where my Theamer durst not come, although he were sent for, so much he [bered] at that unlookt-for aniwhere.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Tarltons_answere_in_defence_of_his_flat_nose."> Tarltons answere in defence of his flat nose. </span></h2>
<p>I Remember I was once at a Play in the Country, where as Tarltons use was, the Play being done, euery one so pleased to throwe up his Theame: amongst all the rest, one was read to this same effect, word by word.
</p>
<dl><dd><i>Tarlton, I am one of thy friends, and none of thy foes,<br /></i>
</dd><dd><i>Then I prethee tell how thou cam'st by thy flat nose:<br /></i>
</dd><dd><i>Had I beene present at that time on those bankes,<br /></i>
</dd><dd><i>I would haue layd my short sword ouer his long shankes.</i>
</dd></dl>
<p>Tarlton mad at this question, as it was his propertie sooner to take such a matter ill then well, very suddenly returned him this answere:
</p>
<dl><dd><i>Friend or foe, if thou wilt needs know, marke me well,<br /></i>
</dd><dd><i>With parting dogs &amp; beares, then by the ears, this chance fel:<br /></i>
</dd><dd><i>But what of that? though my nose be flat, my credit to saue,<br /></i>
</dd><dd><i>Yet ver well, I can by the smell,<br /></i>
<dl><dd><i>scent an honest man from a knaue.</i>
</dd></dl>
</dd></dl>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<dl><dd> This is the first of the jests written in the first person by someone claiming to have witnessed Tarlton performing on tour.
</dd></dl>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Tarltons_Iest_of_a_Bristowman."> Tarltons Iest of a Bristowman. </span></h2>
<p>When the Queenes Players were restrained in Summer, they trauailed downe to S. Iames his Faire, at Bristowe, where they were worthily entertained both of Londoners, and those Citizens: it happened that a wealthy Citizen, called M. Sunbanke, one morning secretly married his Maid; but not so secret, but it was blowne abroad: that morning, Tarlton and others, walking in the Faire to visit his familiar friends of London, and being in company of Bristow men, they did see M. Sunbancke comming, who had this propertie with his necke, not to stirre it any way, but to turne body &amp; all: it chanced at the Faire end, he stood to pisse against a wall: to whom Tarlton came, and clapping him on the shoulder, God giue you ioy of your marriage, saies he: M. Sunbanke being taken pissing against the wall, would haue lookt backe to thanke him, and suddainly turnes about body and all, in the view of many, and shed all: which so abasht him, that ashamed he tooke into a Tauerne, protesting that he had rather haue spent ten pound: sure sayd the Vintner, the fault is in your necke, who will not turne without the bodies assistance, adn not in M. Tarlton: Call you him M. Tarlton, saies M. Sunbancke? I Sir, saies the Vintner, he is the Queens Iester: he may be whose Iester he will be, but this Iest agrees not with me at this time.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
<ul><li> "Bristowe" is Bristol.
</li></ul>
</li><li> Significance
<ul><li> The Queen's Men are recorded as being paid to perform at the Guildhall in Bristol in <a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Touring_1583" title="Touring 1583">1583</a>, <a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Touring_1586" title="Touring 1586">1586</a>, <a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Touring_1587" title="Touring 1587">1587</a>, and <a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Touring_1588" title="Touring 1588">1588</a>. All of these performances occur during the summer (all but 1588 were recorded as taking place in July) roughly at the same time as the St. James Fair, which was traditionally held at the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_James%27_Priory,_Bristol" class="external text" rel="nofollow">St. James Priory in Bristol</a> on July 25. 
</li><li> The jest infers that Tarlton (and perhaps his fellow players) had social relationships in Bristol with people they knew from London.
</li><li> The last section of the jest (Master Sunbancke's complaint to the Vintner at the tavern) demonstrates that the impact of Tarlton's actions was felt by those provoked even beyond his presence
</li></ul>
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="A_Iest_broken_of_Tarlton_by_a_Country_Gentleman."> A Iest broken of Tarlton by a Country Gentleman. </span></h2>
<p>In the Country where the Queens Players were accepted into a Gentlemans house: the Waggon unloading of the apparell, the Waggoner comes to Tarlton, &amp; both desire him to speake to the Steward for his horses: I will sayes he, and comming to the Steward, Sir, saies Tarlton, where shall our Horses spend the time? The Gentleman looking at Tarlton at that question, suddenly answered, if it please you, or them, let them walke a turne or two: or there is a faire Garden, let them play a game or two at bowles in the Alley, and departs thence about his other businesse. Tarlton commending the suddaine wit of the Steward, said little: but my Steward not quiet, tels to the Gentlewomen aboue, how he had driuen Tarlton to a nonplus with a iest: whereat they all did laugh heartily: which a Seruingman louing Tarlton well, came and told him as much. Tarlton to adde fuell to the fire, and loath to rest thus put off with a iest, goes and gets two of the horses into the Garden, and turns them into the Bowling Alley, who with their heeles made hauacke, being the Gentlemans only pastime: The Ladies aboue from a window, seeing horses in the Garden Alley, cal the Knight, who cries out to Tarlton, Fellow, what meanest thou? nothing Sir, saies he, but two of my horses are at seuen by, for a pecke of Prouender, a switch match: hat I made: now they being in play at bowles, run, run: your steward may come after and crie rub, rub: at which, though they smiled, yet the steward had no thankes for his labour, to set the horses to such an excercise: and they could not blame Tarlton, who did but as he was bidden: but by this Iest Bats (?) and Hay, stable-roome, and all, was plenty.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
<ul><li> (identify country houses that might have been the location for this jest)
</li></ul>
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="How_Tarlton_made_one_of_his_company_vtterly_forsweare_drunkennesse."> How Tarlton made one of his company vtterly forsweare drunkennesse. </span></h2>
<p>At Salisbury Tarlton &amp; his fellowes were to play before the Maior &amp; his brethren: but one of his company, a yong man was so drunke that he could not: whereat Tarlton as mad angry, as he was mad drunke, claps me on his legs a huge payre of boults: the fellow dead asleep felt nothing: when all was done, they conuaied him to the Iayle on a mans backe, and intreated the Iayler to doe God good seruice, and let him lie there till he waked. While they were about their sport the fellow waked, and finding himselfe in durance, and the Iayle hung round with bolts and shaklels, he began to blesse himselfe, and thought sure in his drunknes he had done some mischiefe: with that he called to know, but none came to him, then he thought verely his fault was capitall, and that hee was close prisoner: by and by comes the Keeper, and moaned him, that one so yong should come to so shamefull a death as hanging: anone, another comes, and another with the like, which further put him in a puzzle: but at last comes Tarlton and others, intreating the Keeper, yet it might be, that they might see their fellow ere they went, but hee very hardly was intreated, but at length the poore drunken Signior cal'd out for them: in they come. Oh Tom, sayes Tarlton, hard was thy (?) in drunkenesse to murder this honest man, and our hard hap so, to haue it reported any of our company is hangd for it. O God, O God saies the fellow, is my fault so great? then commend me to all my friends. Well, short tale to make, the fellow forswore drunkennesse if he could escape, and by as cunning a wile to his thinking, they got him out of prison by an escape, and sent him to London before, who was not a little glad he was gone: but see how this Iest wrought, by little and little the fellow left his excessiue drinking, and in time altered his desire of drunkennesse.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
<ul><li> boult: some sort of leg restraint
</li><li> durance: OED 5. Forced confinement, imprisonment; constraint. Now esp. in phr. 
</li></ul>
</li><li> Significance
<ul><li> I have not yet found a record in REED of the Queen's Men performing at Salisbury, however it might have been a stop on the road to <a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Touring_1588" title="Touring 1588">Lyme Regis</a>, where they performed on 3 June, 1588.
</li></ul>
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="How_Tarlton_saued_his_head_from_cutting_off."> How Tarlton saued his head from cutting off. </span></h2>
<p>Tarlton upon a time being in the Countrie, &amp; lodging in an homely Inne, during which time there was a gentleman dwelling in the same towne, somewhat frantick and distraught of his wits: which mad man on a suddaine rusht into Tarltons bed-chamber with his sword drawne, and finding him there in bed, would haue slain him: saying, villain, were it not valiantly done to strike off thy knaues head at one blowe? Tarlton answered, tut sir, thats nothing with your worship to do, you can as easily strike off two heads at one blow as one: wherefore, if you please Ile go downe and call up another, and so you may strike off both our heads at once: the mad-man belieued him, and so let him slip away.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="How_Tarlton_escaped_imprisonment."> How Tarlton escaped imprisonment. </span></h2>
<p>Tarlton hauing beene domineering very late one Night, with two of his friends, and comming homewards along Cheapside, the watch being then set: Master Constable asked, who goes there? three merry men, quoth Tarlton: that is not sufficient, what are you, quoth M. Constable? why saies Tarlton, one of us is an eye-maker, and the other a light maker, which two properties belong unto God onely: commit these blasphemers quoth the Constable: Nay, I pray you good M. Constable be good in your Office, I will approue what I haue sayd to be true. If thou canst, sayes the Constable, you shall passe, otherwise you shall be all three punished. Why quoth Tarlton, this fellow is an eye-maker, because a Spectacle maker, and this other a maker of light, because a Chandler, that makes your darkest night as light as your Lanthorne. The Constable seeing them so pleasant, was well contented, the rest of the Watchmen laughed, and Tarlton with his two companions went home quietly.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
<ul><li> Although this jest is listed among those identified as taking place in the country, he is identified as "coming homewards along Cheapside", which would place him in the City of London.
</li></ul>
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="How_Tarlton_deceiued_a_Countrey_wench."> How Tarlton deceiued a Countrey wench. </span></h2>
<p>The Queenes Plaiers trauelling into the West country to play, and lodging in a little village, some ten miles from Bristow, in which village dwelt a pretty nut-browne Lasse to whom Tarlton made proffer of marriage, protesting that he came from London, purposely to marry her: the simple Maide being proud, to be beloued by such a one, whom she knew to be the Queenes man, without more intreaty yeelded, &amp; being both at the Church together, and M. Parson ready to performe his dutie, and comming to the words of I Richard take thee Joane: nay, stay good Master Parson, I will goe and call my fellowes, and come to you againe: so going out of the Church in haste, returned at leisure; for hauing his horse ready sadled, hee rode toward Bristow, and by the way told his fellowes of his successe with his wench.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
<ul><li> It is unclear from this jest whether the country lass referred to is the wife identified in several of the <a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/TarltonsJests#How_Tarlton_iested_at_his_wife." title="TarltonsJests">City Jests</a>, it would seem from the title that Tarlton left this young woman at the altar.
</li></ul>
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="How_Tarlton_went_to_kill_Crowes."> How Tarlton went to kill Crowes. </span></h2>
<p>It chanced upon a time, as Tarlton went forth with a birding peece into the fields to kill Crowes, hee espied a Daw sitting in a Tree, at which he meant to shoot; but at the same instant, there came one by, to whom he spake in this manner: Sir, quoth he, yonder I see a Daw, which I will shoot at if thee sit: if thee sit, said the other, then she is a Daw indeed: but quoth Tarlton, if she sit not, what is she then? Marry quoth the other, a Daw also: at which words shee immediately flew away: whereupon Tarlton spake merrily in a Rime, as followeth:
</p>
<dl><dd><i>Whether a Daw sit, or whether a Daw flie,</i> <br />
</dd><dd><i>Whether a Daw stand, or whether a Daw lie,</i> <br />
</dd><dd><i>Whether a daw creeke, or whether a Daw crie,</i> <br />
</dd><dd><i>In what a case soeuer a Daw percieuer,</i><br />
</dd><dd><i>A Daw is a Daw, and a Daw shall be euer.</i>
</dd></dl>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="How_a_poore_Beggerman_ouer-reached_Tarlton_by_his_wit."> How a poore Beggerman ouer-reached Tarlton by his wit. </span></h2>
<p>As Tarlton upon a day sate at his owne doore, to whom came a poore old man, &amp; begged a penny for the Lords sake, whereupon Tarlton hauing no single money about him, askt the begger what money he had, no more money master but one single penny. Tarlton being merrily disposed, called for this penny, and hauing receiued it, gaue it to his boy to fetch a pot of Ale, whereat the Begger grew blancke, and began to gather up his wits how to get it againe: the pot of Ale for the Beggers penny being brought, he proferred to drinke to the begger: nay stay awhile Master, quoth the begger, the use is where I was borne, that he that paies for the drinke, must drinke first: thou saist well quoth Tarlton, goe to, Drinke to me then: Whereupon the Begger tooke the Pot, saying, here Master I drinke to you, (and therewithall dranke off every droppe) now Master, if you will pledge me, send for it as I haue done: Tarlton seeing himselfe so ouer-reacht, greatly commended the Beggers wit, and withall in recompence therof, gaue him a teaster: with that the Begger said, that he would most truely pray to God for him: no answered Tarlton, I pray thee pray for thy selfe, for I take no usury for Almes deeds.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
<ul><li> James Orchard Halliwell defined a "teaster" as a sixpence.
</li></ul>
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Of_Tarltons_pleasant_answere_to_a_Gallant.2C_by_the_high-way_side."> Of Tarltons pleasant answere to a Gallant, by the high-way side. </span></h2>
<p>It was Tarltons occasion another time to ride into Suffolke, being furnished with a very leane large horse: and by the way a lustie gallant met him, and in mockage, asked him, what a yard of hiw horse was worth? marry sir, quoth Tarlton, I pray you alight and lift up my horses taile, and they in that shop will tell you the price of a yard.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
<ul><li> I have not yet found a record of the Queen's Men performing in Suffolk.
</li></ul>
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="How_Tarlton_would_haue_drowned_his_wife."> How Tarlton would haue drowned his wife. </span></h2>
<p>Upon a time, Tarlton and his wife (as passengers) came sailing from Southampton towards London, a mightie storme arose, and endangered the Ship, whereupon the Captaine thereof, charged euery man to throw into the sea the heauiest thing he could best spare, to the end to lighten somewhat the Ship: Tarlton, that had his wife there, offered to throw her ouer-board, but the company rescued her, and being asked wherefore he meant to do? he answered shee was the heauiest thing I haue, and I can best spare her.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
<ul><li> This jest pre-figures modern jokes about wives.
</li></ul>
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="How_Tarlton_made_his_Will_and_Testament."> How Tarlton made his Will and Testament. </span></h2>
<p>Of late there was a Gentleman liuing in England, that wheresoeuer he dined, would of euery dish conuey a modicum thereof into his Gownesleeue: which Gentleman being upon a time at dinner at a Gentlemans house in the Country, there he used his aforesaid quality in the company of M. Tarlton, who perceiuing it, said thus unto the company: My masters, I am now determined before you all, to make my last Will and Testament: and first, I bequeath my soule to God my creator, and my body to be buried in the sleeue of yonder Gentlemans Gowne: and with that stepping to him, he turned up the Gowne sleeue, whereout here dropt a bird, and there a bird, with choise of much other good cheere, hee still shaking it, saying, I meant this sleeue Gentlemen, this sleeue I meant.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="How_Tarlton_called_a_Gentleman_Knaue_by_craft."> How Tarlton called a Gentleman Knaue by craft. </span></h2>
<p>Within a while after, as the same Gentleman and Tarlton passed through a fielde together, a Crow in a Tree cryed, kaw, kaw: see yonder Tarlton, quoth the Gentleman, yonder Crow calleth thee knaue: no sir (he answered) he beckens to your worship as the better man.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Tarltons_Iest_of_a_Country_wench."> Tarltons Iest of a Country wench. </span></h2>
<p>Tarlton going towards Hogsdon, met a Country maid comming to market, her Pace stumblind down she fell ouer and ouer, shewing all that euer God sent her, and then rising up againe, she turned her round about unto Master Tarlton, and said, Gods body sir, did you euer see the like before? No in good sooth, quoth Tarlton, neuer but once in London.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="How_Tarlton_deceiued_an_Inne-holder_at_Sandwich."> How Tarlton deceiued an Inne-holder at Sandwich. </span></h2>
<p>Upon a time when the Plaiers were put to silence, Tarlton and his boy frolicke so long in the Country, that all their money was gone, and being a great way from London, they knew not what to doe; but as want is the whetstone of wit, Tarlton gathereth his conceit together, and practised a tricke to beare him up to London without money, &amp; thus it was: Unto an Inne in Sandwich they went, and there lay for two daies at great charge, although he had no money to pay for the same: the third morning he had his man go downe and male-content himselfe before his Hoast and his Hoastesse, a mumbling say to himselfe, Lord Lord, what a scalde master doe I serue, this it is to serue such Seminary Priests and Jeiuits, now euen as I am an honest boy, Ile leaue him in the lurch, and shift for my selfe: here's a doe about penance and mortification, as though (forsooth) Christ hath not died enough for all: The boy mumbled out these his instructions so dissembling, that it strooke a jealousie in the Inne-holders heart, that out of doubt his master was a Seminary Priest; whereupon he presently sent for the Constable, and told him all the foresaid matter, and so went by both together to attach Tarlton in his chamber, who purposely had shut himselfe close in, and betaken him to his knees, and to his crosses, to make the matter seeme more suspitious, which they espying through the key-hole, made no more adoe, but in they rushed, and arrested him for a Seminary Priest, discharged his score, bore his, and his boyes charges up to London, and there in hope to haue rich rewards, presented him to M. Fleetwood, the old Recorder of London: but now marke the Iest; when the Recorder saw Tarlton, and knew him passing well, entertained him very courteously, and all to be foold the Inne-holder and his mate, and sent them away with fleas in their eares: but when Tarlton saw himselfe discharged out of their hands, hee stood iesting and pointing at their folly, and so taught them by cunning more wit and thrift against another time.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
<ul><li> It is striking that in a time of such religious uncertainty that Tarlton should pretend to be a Catholic priest just to get out of paying his inn bill.
</li></ul>
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Of_Tarltons_Wrongfull_accusation."> Of Tarltons Wrongfull accusation. </span></h2>
<p>Vpon a time Tarlton was wrongfully accused for getting of a Gentlemans Maid with child and for the same, brought before a Justice in Kente, which Justice said as followeth: It is a mervaile (M. Tarlton) that you being a Gentleman of good qualitie, and one of her Maiesties servants, would venture thus to get Maies with childe. Nay rather (quoth Tarlton) were a maruell, if a maid had gotten me with child.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Tarlton_deceived_by_a_Country_wench."> Tarlton deceived by a Country wench. </span></h2>
<p>Tarlton trauelling to play abroad, was in a Towne where in the Inne was a pretty maid, whose fauour was placed in a corner of Tarltons affection: and talking with her, shee appoynted to meet him at the bottom of a paire of staires. Night and the houre came, and the maid subtilly sent downe her Mistresse: whome Tarlton catching in his armes, Art come, wench, saies hee? Out alas, sayes the Mistres, not knowing who it was. Tarlton hearing it was the Mistres, start aside, and the maid came downe with a candle, and shee espyde a glimpse of Tarlton in the darke, who stept into another roome. How now, Mistres, said the maid? Something (said shee) affrighted me, some man sure, for I heard him speake. No, no, Mistresse, said the Maid, it is no man, it was a Bull calf that I shut into a roome, till Iohn our Pounder came to haue pounded him for a stray. Had I thought that (saith she) I would haue hit him such a knocke on his forehead, that his hornes should neuer haue grac'd his Coxcombe, and so she departs up againe, afraid. But how Tarlton tooke this jest, think you.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="How_Tarlton_could_not_abide_a_Cat.2C_and_deceiued_himselfe."> How Tarlton could not abide a Cat, and deceiued himselfe. </span></h2>
<p>In the Country Tarlton told his [?] he was a Coniurer. I sir (sayes she) I had pewter stolne off my shelfe the other day, help me to it, and I will forgiue you all the pots of Ale you owe mee, which is sixteene dozen. Sayes Tarlton, To morrow morning the Diuell shall helpe you to it, or I will trounce him. Morning came, and the Oastresse and he met in a roome by themselves. Tarlton, to passe the time with excercise of his wit, with Circles and tricks falls to coniure, hauing no more skill then a dogge. But see the iest, how contrarily it fell out: as he was calling out, mons, pons, simul &amp; sons, and such like, a Cat (unexpected) leapt from the gutter window, which sight so amazed Tarlton, that he skipt thence, &amp; threw his Hostesse downe, so that he departed with his fellowes, and left her hip out of joynt, being then in the Surgeons hands, and not daring to tell how it came.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="How_Tarlton_and_his_oastesse_of_Waltham_met."> How Tarlton and his oastesse of Waltham met. </span></h2>
<p>Tarlton riding with divers Citizens his friends, to make merry at Waltham, by the way he met with his Oastesse riding toward London, whome he of old acquaintance, saluted. She demands whither they went? Tarlton told her, to make merry at Waltham. Sir (saies she) then let me request your company at my house at the Christopher, and (for old familiarity) spend your money there. Not unlesse you goe backe (saies Tarlton) we will else goe to the Hound. But she (loth to lose their custome) sent to London by her man, &amp; goes back with them, who by the way had much mirth, for she was an exceeding merry honest woman, yet would take anything: which Tarlton hearing, as wise as he was (thinking her of his minde) he was deceiued: yet he askt her if the biggest bed in her house were able to hold two of their bignesse (meaning himself &amp; her?) Yes (saies she) and tumble up and down at pleasure. Yea, one upon another, saies Tarlton? And under too, saies she. Well, to haue their custome, she agreed to euery thing, like a subtill Oastesse: and it fell so out that Tarlton hauing her in a roome at her house, askt her which of those two beds were big enough for them two? This, said she: therefore goe to bed sweet-heart, Ile come to thee. Masse (saies Tarlton) were my Bootes off, I would indeed. I'le help you, Sir (saies she) if you please. Yeah (thought Tarlton) is the wind in that doore? come on then. And she very diligently begins to pull, till one boot was half off. Now (saies she) this being hard to doe, let me try my cunning on the other, and so get off both. But hauing both half off his legs, she left him alone in the Shoeemakers stocks, and got her to London, where Tarlton, was three houres, and had no help. But being eas'd of his paine, he made this Ryme for a Theame, singing of it all the way to London:
</p>
<dl><dd><i>Women are Wanton, and hold it no sinne,</i>
</dd><dd><i>By tricks and devices to pull a man in.</i>
</dd></dl>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Tarltons_meeting_with_his_Countrey_acquaintance_at_Ilford."> Tarltons meeting with his Countrey acquaintance at Ilford. </span></h2>
<p>On a Sunday, Tarlton rode to Ilford, where his father kept: and dining with him at his Sisters, there came in diuers of the Countrey to see him, amongst whom was one plaine Countrey plough-iogger, who said hee was of Tarltons kin, &amp; so called him cousin. But Tarlton demanded demanded of his father if it were so? but he knew no such matter: whereupon saies Tarlton, where he be of my kin or no, I will be cousin to him ere we part, if all the drinke in Ilford will doe it. So upon this they caroused freely, &amp; the Clowne was then in his Cue so that (in briefe) they were both in soundly. Night came &amp; Tarlton would not let his cousin goe, but they would lye together that night, meaning to drinke at their departure next morning. Tarlton would by wit leaue him in the lash, since power would not. But see the jest: That night the plaine fellow so pist Tarlton in his bed, thinking he had been against the Church wal that he was faine to cry for a fresh shirt to shift him, So when al was well, they must needs drinke at parting: where indeed (to seale kindred soundly) the fellow had his loade: for hearing that his cousin Talton, was gone to London, Zounds he would follow, that he would, none could hold him: and meaning so goe towards London; his aime was to goe, that he went towards Rumford to sell his Hogs.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="How_a_Maid_drove_Tarlton_to_a_Non-plus."> How a Maid drove Tarlton to a Non-plus. </span></h2>
<p>Tarlton, meeting with a wily Country wench, who gaue him quip for quip; Sweetheart (said hee) would my flesh were in thine. So would I, Sir (saies shee) I would your nose were in my, I know where. Tarlton, angered at this, said no more, but goes forward.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Tarltons_answer_to_a_question."> Tarltons answer to a question. </span></h2>
<p>One asked Tarlton why Munday was called Sundaies fellow? Because he is a sausie fellow (saies Tarlton) to compare with that holy day. But it may be, Munday thinkes himself Sundayes fellow, because it followes Sunday, and is next after: he comes a day after the faire for that. Nay (saies the fellow) but if two Sundayes fall together, Munday then baybe the first, and it would shew well too. Yes (saies Tarlton) but if thy nose stood under they mouth, it would shew better, and be more for thy profit. How for my profit, said the fellow? Marry (said Tarlton) neuer to be cold in winter, being so neere euery dogs taile. The fellow seeing a foolish question had a foolish answere, laid his legges on his neck, and got him gone. 
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Tarlton_desire_of_enough_for_money."> Tarlton desire of enough for money. </span></h2>
<p>Tarlton comming into a Market towne bought Oates for his horse, and desired enough for money: the man said. You shall, Sir and gave him two halfe pecks for one. Tarlton thought his Horse should that night fare largely, and comes to him with this Rime:
</p>
<dl><dd><i>Iack Nag, he brag, and loftie braue it,</i>
</dd><dd><i>I have enough for mony, and thou shalt have it.</i>
</dd></dl>
<p>But when Iack Nag smelt to them they were so musty, that he would none (God thanke you, Master) which Tarlton seeing, runnes into the Market, and would slash and cut. But til the next Market day the fellow was not to be found, and before then Tarlton must be gone.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="How_Tarltons_Dogge_lickt_vp_six_pence."> How Tarltons Dogge lickt vp six pence. </span></h2>
<p>Tarlton in his Trauaile had a Dogge of fine qualities, amongst the rest, he would carry six pence in the end of his tongue, of which he would brag often and say, Never was the like. Yes, saies a Lady, mine is more strange, for he will beare a French crowne in his mouth: no, saies Tarlton, I think not: lend me a French crowne, saies the Lady, and you shall see: truly Madame, I haue it not but if your dog will carry a crackt English crowne, here it is: but the Lady perceiued not the iest, but was desirous to see the dogs trick of six pence. Tarlton threw down a teaster, and said, Bring Sirra: and by fortune the Dog took by a Counter, and let the money lie: a Gentlewoman by, seeing that, askt him how long he would hold it? An houre, saies Tarlton: that is pretty, said the Gentlewoman, let's see that: meane time she tooke up the sixe pence, and willed him to let them see the money againe: when he did see it, it was a Counter, and he made this Rime.
</p>
<dl><dd><i>Alas, alas, how came all this to passe?</i>
</dd><dd><i>The worlds worse then it was:</i>
</dd><dd><i>For silver turns to brasse.</i>
</dd></dl>
<p>I, sayes the Lady, &amp; the dog hath made his master an Asse: but Tarlton would neuer trust to his Dogs tricks more.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Tarltons_Iest_of_a_Horse_and_a_Man."> Tarltons Iest of a Horse and a Man. </span></h2>
<p>In the City of Norwich, Tarlton was on a time inuited to an hunting: where there was a goodly Gentlewoman, that brauely mounted on a blacke horse, rode exceeding well, to the wonder of all the beholders, and neither hedge nor ditch stood in her way, but Pegasus her horse (for so may we tearme him for swiftnesse) flew ouer all, and she sate him aswell. When euery one returned home, some at Supper commended his Hound, others his Hawke, and shee aboue all, her Horse: and, said she, I loue no liuing creature so well (at this instant) as my gallant horse: yes Lady, a man better, saies Tarlton. Indeed no, said shee, not now: for since my last husband dyed, I hate them most, unlesse you can giue me medicines to make me loue them. Tarlton made this iest instantly: 
</p>
<dl><dd><i>Why, a Horse mingeth Whay, Madam, a Man mingeth Amber,</i>
</dd><dd><i>A Horse is for your Way, Madam, but a man for your Chamber.</i>
</dd></dl>
<p>God a mercy, Tarlton, said the men: which the Gentlewoman noting, seeing they tooke exceptions at her words, to make all well, answered thus:
</p>
<dl><dd><i>That a Horse is my chiefe opinion now, I deny not,</i>
</dd><dd><i>And when a man doth me more good in my chamber, I him defie not.</i>
</dd></dl>
<p>But till then giue me leaue to loue something: then something will please you, said Tarlton. I am glad of that, there I pray God send you a good thing, or none at all.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Tarltons_talke_with_a_pretty_Woman."> Tarltons talke with a pretty Woman. </span></h2>
<p>Gentlewoman, said Tarlton, and the rest as you sit, I can tell you strange things: now many Gallants at Supper noted one woman, who being little and pretty, to unfit her prettinesse, had a great wide mouth, which she seeming to hide, would pinch in her speeches, and speake small, but was desirous to heare newes. Tarlton told at his comming from London to Norwich, a Proclamation was made that euery man should haue two wiues. now Iesus quod she is it possible? I Gentlewoman, and other wise able to, for contrarily women haue a larger preeminence, for euery woman must haue three husbands: Now Iawsus, said the Gentlewoman, and with wonder shewes the full widenesse of her mouth, which all the table smil'd at: which she perceiuing, would answere no more. Now Mistris, said, Tarlton, your mouth is lesse then euer it was, for now it is able to say nothing. Thou art a cogging Knaue, said she. Masse, and that is somthing yet, said Tarlton, your mouth shall be as wide as euer it was, for that Iest.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="A_Iest_of_Tarlton_to_a_great_man."> A Iest of Tarlton to a great man. </span></h2>
<p>There was a great huge man, 3. yards in the wast, at S. Edmondsbury in Suffolk, that died but of late daies (one M. Blague by name) &amp; a good kinde Justice too, carefull for the poore, this Justice met with Tarlton in Norwich: Tarlton, said he, Giue me thy hand: But, you Sir, being richer, may giue me a greater gift, giue me your body: and enbracing him, could not halfe compasse him: being merry in talke, said the Justice: Tarlton, tell me one thing, what is the difference betwixt a Flea and a Louse? Marry, Sir; said Tarlton, as much and like difference, as twixt you and me: I like a Flea (see else) can skip nimbly: But you, like a fat Louse creepe slowly, and you can go no faster, though Butchers are ouer you, ready to knock you on the head. Thou art a knaue, quoth the Justice. I, Sir, I knew that ere I came hither, else I had not been here now, for euer one knaue (making a stop) seekes out another. The Justice understanding him, laughed heartily.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Tarltons_Iest_to_a_maid_in_the_darke."> Tarltons Iest to a maid in the darke. </span></h2>
<p>Tarlton going in the darke, groping out his way, heares the tread of some one to meet him. Who goes there, saies he? A man, or a monster? said the maid, A monster: said Tarlton, A candle hoe: and seeing who it was, Indeed said he, A monster, Ile be sworne: for thy teeth are longer then thy beard, I Sir, said the maid, speake no more then you see, for women goe inuisible now adayes.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Tarltons_Iest_to_a_Dogge."> Tarltons Iest to a Dogge. </span></h2>
<p>Tarlton and his fellows, being in the Bishop of Worcesters Celler, and being largely laid to, Tarlton had his rouse, and going through the streets, a Dogge (in the middle of the street, asleep, on a dunghill) seeing Tarlton reele on him, on the suddaine barkt. How now Dog, saies Tarlton, are you in your humors? and many daies after it was a by-word to a man being drunke, that he was in his humors.
</p>
<ul><li> Gloss
</li><li> Significance
</li></ul>
<p><b>FINIS.</b>
</p>
<h2> <span class="mw-headline" id="Notes">Notes</span></h2>

<!-- 
NewPP limit report
Preprocessor node count: 144/1000000
Post-expand include size: 0/2097152 bytes
Template argument size: 0/2097152 bytes
Expensive parser function count: 0/100
-->

<!-- Saved in parser cache with key djakacki3:pcache:idhash:100-0!*!0!!en!*!edit=0 and timestamp 20120610054622 -->
<div class="printfooter">
Retrieved from "<a href="http://www.lcc.gatech.edu/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/TARLTONS_PRETTIE_COUNTRIE_IESTS.">http://www.lcc.gatech.edu/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/TARLTONS_PRETTIE_COUNTRIE_IESTS.</a>"</div>
						<div id='catlinks' class='catlinks catlinks-allhidden'></div>											</div>
				</div>
			
			</div><!-- #content -->
		</div><!-- #container -->
		
		<div id="primary" class="widget-area" role="complementary">
			<ul class="xoxo">
						
				<li class="widget-container">
		<h3 class="widget-title"><label for="searchInput">Search</label></h3>
			<form action="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php" id="searchform">
				<input type='hidden' name="title" value="Special:Search"/>
				<input id="searchInput" title="Search Richard Tarlton Project" accesskey="f" type="search" name="search" />
				<input type='submit' name="go" class="searchButton" id="searchGoButton"
				value="Go" title="Go to a page with this exact name if exists" />

			</form>
	</li>
		<li class="widget-container logo">
			<a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Main_Page" title="Visit the main page">
				<img src="http://www.lcc.gatech.edu/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/images/8/8b/TarltonKey.png" alt="Site Logo" />
			</a>
		</li>
					
			</ul>
		</div><!-- #primary .widget-area -->

	</div><!-- #main -->

	<div id="footer" role="contentinfo" >
		<div id="colophon">
		
			<div id="footer-widget-area" role="complementary">
			
				<div id="first" class="widget-area">
					<ul class="xoxo">
			
				 <li id="ca-nstab-main" class="selected"><a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/TARLTONS_PRETTIE_COUNTRIE_IESTS." title="View the content page [c]" accesskey="c">Page</a></li>
				 <li id="ca-talk" class="new"><a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php?title=Talk:TARLTONS_PRETTIE_COUNTRIE_IESTS.&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" title="Discussion about the content page [t]" accesskey="t">Discussion</a></li>
				 <li id="ca-viewsource"><a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php?title=TARLTONS_PRETTIE_COUNTRIE_IESTS.&amp;action=edit" title="This page is protected.&#10;You can view its source [e]" accesskey="e">View source</a></li>
				 <li id="ca-history"><a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php?title=TARLTONS_PRETTIE_COUNTRIE_IESTS.&amp;action=history" title="Past revisions of this page [h]" accesskey="h">History</a></li>					</ul>
				</div><!-- #first .widget-area -->
			
				<div id="second" class="widget-area">
					<ul class="xoxo">
									<li id="t-whatlinkshere"><a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Special:WhatLinksHere/TARLTONS_PRETTIE_COUNTRIE_IESTS." title="List of all wiki pages that link here [j]" accesskey="j">What links here</a></li>
				<li id="t-recentchangeslinked"><a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Special:RecentChangesLinked/TARLTONS_PRETTIE_COUNTRIE_IESTS." title="Recent changes in pages linked from this page [k]" accesskey="k">Related changes</a></li>
<li id="t-specialpages"><a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Special:SpecialPages" title="List of all special pages [q]" accesskey="q">Special pages</a></li>
				<li id="t-permalink"><a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php?title=TARLTONS_PRETTIE_COUNTRIE_IESTS.&amp;oldid=638" title="Permanent link to this revision of the page">Permanent link</a></li>					</ul>
				</div><!-- #second .widget-area -->
				
				<div id="third" class="widget-area">
					<ul class="xoxo" >
											<li id="pt-anonuserpage"><a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/User:24.99.206.88" title="The user page for the IP address you are editing as [.]" accesskey="." class="new">24.99.206.88</a></li>
											<li id="pt-anontalk"><a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/User_talk:24.99.206.88" title="Discussion about edits from this IP address [n]" accesskey="n" class="new">Talk for this IP address</a></li>
											<li id="pt-anonlogin"><a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php?title=Special:UserLogin&amp;returnto=TARLTONS_PRETTIE_COUNTRIE_IESTS.&amp;returntoquery=printable%3Dyes" title="You are encouraged to log in; however, it is not mandatory [o]" accesskey="o">Log in</a></li>
										</ul>
				</div><!-- #third .widget-area -->

				<div id="fourth" class="widget-area">
					<ul class="xoxo">
										<li id="lastmod"> This page was last modified on 26 June 2011, at 14:35.</li>
																<li id="viewcount">This page has been accessed 1,371 times.</li>
																<li id="privacy"><a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Richard_Tarlton_Project:Privacy_policy" title="Richard Tarlton Project:Privacy policy">Privacy policy</a></li>
																<li id="about"><a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Richard_Tarlton_Project:About" title="Richard Tarlton Project:About">About Richard Tarlton Project</a></li>
																<li id="disclaimer"><a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Richard_Tarlton_Project:General_disclaimer" title="Richard Tarlton Project:General disclaimer">Disclaimers</a></li>
																</ul>
				</div><!-- #fourth .widget-area -->				
				
			</div><!-- #footer-widget-area -->
		
			<div id="site-info">
				<a href="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/index.php/Main_Page" rel="home">Richard Tarlton Project</a>
			</div><!-- #site-info -->
			<div id="site-generator">Proudly powered by
				<a href="http://mediawiki.org/" rel="generator">MediaWiki</a>
				and the <a href="http://wordpress.org/extend/themes/twentyten" rel="generator">TwentyTen WordPress theme</a>.
			</div>
		</div><!-- #colophon -->
	</div><!-- #footer -->

</div><!-- #wrapper -->


<script src="/~djakacki3/tarlton/wiki/load.php?debug=false&amp;lang=en&amp;modules=startup&amp;only=scripts&amp;printable=1&amp;skin=twentyten&amp;*"></script>
<script>if ( window.mediaWiki ) {
	mediaWiki.config.set({"wgCanonicalNamespace": "", "wgCanonicalSpecialPageName": false, "wgNamespaceNumber": 0, "wgPageName": "TARLTONS_PRETTIE_COUNTRIE_IESTS.", "wgTitle": "TARLTONS PRETTIE COUNTRIE IESTS.", "wgAction": "view", "wgArticleId": 100, "wgIsArticle": true, "wgUserName": null, "wgUserGroups": ["*"], "wgCurRevisionId": 638, "wgCategories": [], "wgBreakFrames": false, "wgRestrictionEdit": ["autoconfirmed"], "wgRestrictionMove": ["autoconfirmed"]});
}
</script>
<script>if ( window.mediaWiki ) {
	mediaWiki.loader.load(["mediawiki.util", "mediawiki.legacy.wikibits", "mediawiki.legacy.ajax"]);
	mediaWiki.loader.go();
}
</script>

<script>if ( window.mediaWiki ) {
	mediaWiki.user.options.set({"ccmeonemails":0,"cols":80,"contextchars":50,"contextlines":5,"date":"default","diffonly":0,"disablemail":0,"disablesuggest":0,"editfont":"default","editondblclick":0,"editsection":1,"editsectiononrightclick":0,"enotifminoredits":0,"enotifrevealaddr":0,"enotifusertalkpages":1,"enotifwatchlistpages":0,"extendwatchlist":0,"externaldiff":0,"externaleditor":0,"fancysig":0,"forceeditsummary":0,"gender":"unknown","hideminor":0,"hidepatrolled":0,"highlightbroken":1,"imagesize":2,"justify":0,"math":1,"minordefault":0,"newpageshidepatrolled":0,"nocache":0,"noconvertlink":0,"norollbackdiff":0,"numberheadings":0,"previewonfirst":0,"previewontop":1,"quickbar":1,"rcdays":7,"rclimit":50,"rememberpassword":0,"rows":25,"searchlimit":20,"showhiddencats":0,"showjumplinks":1,"shownumberswatching":1,"showtoc":1,"showtoolbar":1,"skin":"twentyten","stubthreshold":0,"thumbsize":2,"underline":2,"uselivepreview":0,"usenewrc":0,"watchcreations":0,"watchdefault":0,"watchdeletion":0,
	"watchlistdays":3,"watchlisthideanons":0,"watchlisthidebots":0,"watchlisthideliu":0,"watchlisthideminor":0,"watchlisthideown":0,"watchlisthidepatrolled":0,"watchmoves":0,"wllimit":250,"variant":"en","language":"en","searchNs0":true,"searchNs1":false,"searchNs2":false,"searchNs3":false,"searchNs4":false,"searchNs5":false,"searchNs6":false,"searchNs7":false,"searchNs8":false,"searchNs9":false,"searchNs10":false,"searchNs11":false,"searchNs12":false,"searchNs13":false,"searchNs14":false,"searchNs15":false});;mediaWiki.loader.state({"user.options":"ready"});
}
</script></body>
</html>



	